בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is נ"ט, Nun Tes, 59,
we're in the middle of נ"ח עמוד ב', Nun Ches Amud Beis,
and we pick up, what do we pick up right after it
speaks about קין Kayin marrying his sister?
Maybe we'll start from there, from the תא שמע, Tashma, which is
about ten lines from the top, end of the line, or twelve
lines from the top. Is that too soon or is that roughly
where you got to yesterday? Okay. And we're in the middle of
really of figuring out what are the עריות arayos that apply for
בני נח. Bnei Noach.
And yesterday, you know, we had had an interesting discussion, first of
all an opinion about the issue of רציחה, retzicha, is there a
unique הלכה halacha in terms of בני נח? Bnei Noach? How does
that apply to עוברים, ubarim, to fetuses? We know that ישראל Yisrael
is not considered a capital crime when it comes to fetuses, abortion,
בני נח Bnei Noach it is included in שבע מצוות בני נח
Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach because of אדם באדם. adam ba'adam. You know,
I've often thought that maybe that has to do with an idea
similar to the idea of less than a פרוטה, prutah, that by
בני נח Bnei Noach there is not a, the same idea of
like שיעורים, shiurim, degrees doesn't apply, like it basically is anything that
somehow falls under the rubric, there's no minimum standard. However, we will
see whether that really works because there are areas which the גמרא
Gemara is going to get to where actually there does seem to
be like more classic שיעורים shiurim or definitions. But it also is
interesting because in the debates around, what do you call it, around
abortion within הלכה, halacha, you know, like in some areas, you know,
for say like, I mean it's an interesting question for example, getting
your animal sterilized, can you bring it to a non-Jew to do
it? Well, is it included in the שבע מצוות בני נח? Sheva
Mitzvos Bnei Noach? Is it a problem of לפני עיוור, lifnei iver,
right? So that's like an important question that actually comes up very
למעשה. lamayseh. But you know here, like if somebody has an abortion,
gets it through a non-Jewish doctor, that's a clear לפני עיוור lifnei
iver of what do you call it, of one of the שבע
מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach. Does that tell you, does
that reflect on the fact that it's considered to be an עבירה
averah for Jews? Maybe not a death penalty and ex- you know
punishable by execution and so on, it's not רציחה, retzicha, but does
it reflect on the fact that it's an עבירה averah for Jews
or not? That actually we'll get to, it'll come up in the
תוספות Tosafot that we're going to see. So we're going to see
that later today. Also interestingly from what was done yesterday was the
whole issue about like women within the context of בני נח. Bnei
Noach. So on the one hand being very non-שיעורים, shiurim, following this
idea of non-שיעורים, shiurim, non-formal requirements in terms of adjudication, twenty-three, it
could be even an עד אחד, ed echad, you know, it could
be without התראה, hasra'ah, but the one sort of thing that was
excluded interestingly was women. And then it goes through a whole discussion
about that women though are in the other aspects of the שבע
מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach. Okay, but most and the
final thing just to review from yesterday that was particularly interesting was
the idea that within the realm of עריות, arayot, if it is
עריות arayot that's not included in בני נח, Bnei Noach, one classic
example is that for בני נח Bnei Noach marriage is strictly defined
only by בעולת בעל, be'ulat ba'al, only by the reality of having
had intercourse in the context of marriage, there's no concept of אירוסין.
erusin. So a case of נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'urasah, for example, or
any woman who's an ארוסה arusa would not be included in בני
נח. Bnei Noach. But if a non-Jew Gentile had intercourse with a
Jewish woman who was a נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'urasah, since under our
category that is considered an ערווה, ervah, and since the act was
with one of us, was with a Jewish woman, that actually would
be punishable, but punishable sort of following our laws in terms of
סקילה skilah and so on, rather than in terms of their laws.
So that was actually interesting,
when it intersects with a Jewish person, somehow we're not, you know
and it's punishable by our laws, it's our laws are going to
cover as well. So those are some of the issues that came
up yesterday. We'll get back to the abortion one which is particularly
interesting and relevant later today. But anyway, now we're still in the
middle of determining what is the scope of the עריות. arayos. So
you basically had had two opinions. You had a whole complicated issue
about whatever, about somebody who converted and so on, but the basic
positions are רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that limits it to those things
that a Jew is liable to death penalty for, and he learns
it from the פסוק pasuk of, you know, על כן יעזוב איש
את
אביו ואת אמו Al kein ya'azov ish es aviv v'es imo and
so on, and he interprets that whole פסוק pasuk to be father,
mother, father's wife and so on, and all these people that, you
know, male, animal, etc., all these things that are in the death
penalty. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't focus on the death penalty,
and he basically thinks that things that are based
on the issue of אחווה, achva, like sisters would be, any would
be, father's sister, your own sister, etc., even
and even things that is not the death penalty. But that's him
where the definition, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva focuses marriage is relevant within
the context of עריות arayot and specifically the death. death penalty and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer not marriage and specifically and focusing on the
issue of sisters. The other relevant thing is that relations are defined
through the mother matrilineally not through the father, and you know, in
a way that sort of makes sense because you know who the
mother is. And that everybody agrees to. Okay, so those are—so with
that in mind, we continue discussing these issues of the עריות arayot
for בני נח. Bnei Noach. We pick up on נ"ח עמוד ב',
Nun Chet Amud Bet, תא שמע, Tashma, end of the line about
twelve lines from the top. תא שמע: Tashma: מפני מה לא נשא
אדם את בתו?
Mifnei mah lo
nasa Adam et bito? Why did אדם Adam not marry his daughter?
Because he had his—he had a wife.
Yes, as תוספות Tosafot sort of says, after חוה Chava sinned, maybe
she was going to die as a result of the sin; still
not exactly clear—in the end, she didn't die. But anyway, it doesn't
matter. Like why, in theory, you know, he could have had any
woman
he wanted. So—all two of them. So why didn't he marry his
daughter? כדי שישא קין את אחותו. Kedei sheyisa Kayin et achoto. He
did it because his son needed a wife. שנאמר: Shenemar: כי אמרתי
עולם חסד יבנה. ki amarti olam chesed yibaneh. It was a חסד
chesed that אברהם Avraham gave this woman that he could have claimed
for his own and gave it to קין, Kayin, his son, for
a wife. Okay. הא לאו הכי אסירא. Ha lav hachi asira. Now,
that suggests that without that, he would have—without the fact
that קין Kayin needed to get married,
a sister would have been forbidden to בני נח. Bnei Noach. So
this supports רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that focuses on sister, and it's
against רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who focuses on death penalty; sister in
Jewish law is not death penalty. No, כיון דאשתרי אשתרי. Kivan de'ishtarei
ishtarei. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi
Akiva would say
once קין Kayin was allowed to marry a sister, בני נח Bnei
Noach in general were allowed to marry their sister. Okay. And again,
since sister is not death penalty for ישראל. Yisrael. רש"י Rashi quotes
the פסוק—I pasuk mean, it clearly seems to be in the background
here—that the פסוק pasuk when it speaks about a man marrying his
sister, it says, you know, it
says—the פסוק pasuk actually uses the word חסד. chesed. רש"י Rashi quotes
it: what's the פסוק? pasuk? חסד הוא. Chesed hu. It
says—where—I can't think of the פסוק pasuk offhand. Oh, here: ואיש אשר
יקח את אחותו בת אביו... חסד הוא. ve'ish asher yikach et achoto
bat aviv... chesed hu.
So it's a very bizarre phrase, חסד, chesed, in the פרשה parsha
of עריות arayot to speak about not marrying your sister. So רש"י
Rashi connects the two; רש"י Rashi on the תורה Torah says the
same thing, that although I allowed it for קין, Kayin, that was
a חסד. chesed. Okay, but fundamentally sister is forbidden for ישראל. Yisrael.
And here the question is whether sister is for בני נח. Bnei
Noach. So one answer is it was for all בני נח, Bnei
Noach, קין Kayin was an exception. Or no, once the allowance was
made for קין, Kayin, it was מותר mutar for all בני נח.
Bnei Noach. Okay. Yes?
Is there any concept related here about that
חוה Chava
came from אדם's Adam body and the daughter—I mean...
Oh, that's interesting. Yeah, that's an interesting idea.
They came from their body?
No, the daughter was born naturally, but yes. But interesting. I have
to process that. That's an interesting question.
The daughter also from the same mother and the same father, so
how do you...
I understand. Okay. But according to this approach, according to רבי אליעזר—according
Rabbi Eliezer to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, בני נח Bnei Noach is
מותר באחותו. mutar be'achoto.
And which side?
No. No. According to—yes, yes. According to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if it's not an איסור, issur, if it's
not a חיוב מיתה, chiyuv mita, בני נח Bnei Noach is מותר
לגמרי. mutar legamri. Okay? And therefore, אחותו achoto is only a כרת.
karet. The basic thing to know is that sisters are, you know,
things that are through brothers—sisters are כרת karet and not מיתה. mita.
So a man's sister, his father's sister, his mother's sister—all of those
are basically כרת karet and not מיתה. mita. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says that those are completely בני נח Bnei Noach is מותר.
mutar. Yes, full sister, בני נח Bnei Noach is מותר. mutar. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says בני נח Bnei
Noach in general are generally are אסור, assur, but this was a
special חסד chesed for קין. Kayin. But this issue of mother—mother or
whatever,
for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, who says sisters are אסור, assur, it
would
be—sister on the father's side would be מותר. mutar. But either way,
קין Kayin was allowed, even a full sister. According to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer it was special allowance and according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that's the rule.
So according to that other opinion, then it's not even like a
פטור אבל אסור, patur aval assur, it's like completely מותר? mutar?
Yeah. There's no פטור אבל אסור patur aval assur by בני נח.
Bnei Noach. Okay. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, okay.
אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: כותי מותר בבתו. Kuti mutar bevito.
Now, רב הונא Rav Huna says now, so this is the position
that's not רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and not רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
He says daughter is permissible. Neither of them said daughter was permissible.
Daughter is a חיוב מיתה. chiyuv mita. So now, what's that based
on? So רש"י Rashi basically says, well, this is just not a
category, this is just a close reading of the פסוק pasuk of
על כן יעזב איש את אביו ואת אמו. Al ken ya'azov ish
et aviv ve'et imo. So it's only things that are included in
that פסוק. pasuk. So based on the דרשות drashot yesterday, what's included
in that פסוק? pasuk? Father, mother, father's wife... well, right, father's wife,
a male, an animal,
but not sister and not daughter. Okay? Only the things that are
explicitly included in that פסוק. pasuk. All right, so that's what he
says. And by the way, that's the way the רמב"ם Rambam rules.
Okay. מותר בבתו. Mutar bevito. ואם
תאמר, Ve'im tomar, if that's true, מפני מה לא נשא אדם את
בתו? mifnei mah lo nasa Adam et bito? So if for בני
נח Bnei Noach it was מותר בבתו. mutar bevito. Why didn't אדם
Adam marry his daughter? כדי שישא קין את האחות. Kedei sheyisa Kayin
et ha’achot. Yes, halachically he could, but to allow Cain to marry
a sister. עולם
חסד יבנה. Olam chesed yibaneh. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי, V’ika d’amrei, others say,
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, כותי אסור בבתו, Kuti assur bevito,
forbidden. תידא, Teida, שלא נשא אדם את בתו, shelo nasa Adam et
bito, because the proof is since אדם Adam didn't that shows you
that בני נח אסור. Bnei Noach assur. ולא היא, Veloha, that's not
a proof. התם מאי טעמא, Hatam mai ta’ama, כדי שישא קין את
האחות? kedei sheyisa Kayin et ha’achot? אדם Adam could have, but it
was in order to allow קין Kayin to marry a sister, משום
דעולם חסד יבנה. mishum de’olam chesed yibaneh. Okay. So again you've got
three positions: one is that she is, that you follow רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer who sort of ignores things through marriage, father's wife, etc.,
but he focuses on sisters, your sister, a man's sister, a man's
father's sister, etc. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who focuses on things that
are אסור assur that are חייבי מיתה מן התורה. chayavei mita min
haTorah. And this last position which is probably within רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, but it excludes the daughter. It's a much more limited, it's
not a category, only those things that emerge from the פסוק. pasuk.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Right, but within the issue
of who is related to you, right, and who is your sister
and so on, assuming sister is אסור assur according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, it would only be through the mother and not through
the father. All right. Now, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says
רב הונא, Rav Huna, I'll say skip, skip that. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, עבד מותר באמו, eved mutar be’imo, a
slave is permitted with his mother. Now, מותר בבתו, mutar bevito, his
daughter. Now בבתו bevito we already saw was debated, but the חידוש
chiddush is אמו. imo. Who’s, nobody’s מותר באמו. mutar be’imo. Nobody says
a בן נח Ben Noach is מותר באמו. mutar be’imo. Right?
So and nobody says that a ישראל Yisrael is מותר באמו. mutar
be’imo. So how is this guy not, not אסור באמו? assur be’imo?
Slave. So, מותר באמו, מותר בבתו. mutar be’imo, mutar bevito. יצא מכלל
כותי ולכלל ישראל לא בא. Yatza miklal Kuti ulekhlal Yisrael lo va.
He’s in neither status. Now what does that mean he’s in neither
status? The point is that he converted. And because he converted, okay,
because an עבד eved undergoes an act of טבילה tevilah and conversion,
etc., he has this basically like כקטן שנולד דמי. k’katan shenolad dami.
He’s a
quasi-ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, and therefore he is אסור ב, assur be, he
is, from a בני נח Bnei Noach law no longer apply to
him. But why is he מותר באמו? mutar be’imo? I mean, you
know, the laws that apply to an עבד, eved, the laws that
apply to a Jew, the prohibitions apply to an עבד. eved. So
the only real reason that he’s מותר באמו, mutar be’imo, theoretically he
really is אסור באמו assur be’imo because he’s, you know, he’s bound
by the לא תעשה'ס, lo ta’aseis, by the negative prohibitions, but because
he has converted and it’s כקטן שנולד דמי, k’katan shenolad dami, therefore
he’s not really related to his mother. Okay, so as opposed to
the issues we had before, that when a non-Jew converts the prohibitions
still remain, that you shouldn't say I left, what, now the Jewish
law is more lenient on me than the non-Jewish law and so
on, right, that’s everything we learned yesterday, so the prohibitions basically remain
even though technically you’re no longer related because כקטן שנולד דמי. k’katan
shenolad dami. Here by case of a slave, you know, they sort
of allowed him to be in this like נישט הי נישט הער
nisht hie nisht her category, like you know in this neither here
nor there type of a category, since he’s not a ישראל Yisrael
he’s not yet entered into Jewish law and saying, oh, Jewish law’s
more lenient than non-Jewish law, so he’s sort of in this middle
category. So it’s very bizarre, right? So anyway, the basic point is
that fundamentally הלכה halakha applies to him, Jewish law, but he’s not
really related anymore to his mother or to his daughter.
In Jewish law what about is there a universal prohibition in cultures
in general about that?
Yeah.
Or is there like a human category or is it only...
Well, he is in the human category. For example, if he had
a daughter now that he converted, she would be אסורה assura because
he is in... so the only... he really is, it’s a deceptive
line in the גמרא. Gemara. He really is covered by standard הלכה.
halakha. But the reason he’s מותר באמו ובבתו mutar be’imo ubevito that
he had when he was a non-Jew, his mother and his daughter
from his time of having been a non-Jew, is because technically he’s
no longer related to them. If he were to now have a
daughter he’d be אסור. assur.
Once his conversion’s finished...
Yes, no, once, that’s the irony, once his conversion is finished he
becomes אסור assur with his mother from, you know, his mother who
he technically is not related, and that’s a Rabbinic law so it
shouldn't get, you shouldn't say, oh, the status of a Jew is
more lenient. But that idea that we're going to say that we're
going to retain your relations from before, the prohibitions apply, but do
we recognize the relations? So the irony is we only recognize those
relations when he becomes a full Jew, okay, and therefore so he
shouldn't feel that Jewish law is more lenient. But when he’s in
this עבד eved status we're not so concerned. Okay, but it’s strange,
like still, being an עבד eved is a quasi-Jew and in the
process of being part of a Jewish household and being governed in
all other areas by Jewish law, so it’s still strange that we're
not concerned that he's going to feel the Jewish law is more
lenient. Yes.
It almost looks like what you'd probably read into it but go
like a limbo thing. Yeah, right, so don't keep people in this
limbo thing.
Right, that could be, right, it is a very sort of nebulous
state. Right, yeah, that’s definitely true. You know what they say: what
do you get if you cross a chicken with a rabbit? נישט
אהין נישט אהער. Nisht ahin nisht aher. Okay, so. All right, fine.
Anyway, so. All right, so now it says like this. Okay, now.
Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רב אלעזר אמר רבי יוחנן: Ki
ata Rav Dimi amar Rav Elazar amar Rabi Yochanan: בן נח שייחד
שפחה לעבדו. Ben Noach she'yichad shifcha l'avdo. So בן נח Ben Noach
that designated a maidservant for his slave. ובא עליה, U'va aleha,
and then the gentile master had intercourse with her, נהרג עליה. neherag
aleha. Now why is he נהרג עליה? neherag aleha? So the גמרא
Gemara earlier said it was a form of גזל. gezel. There is
no marriage for slaves and anyway בני נח Bnei Noach are only
אסור—marriage assur is only defined by בעולת בעל be'ulat ba'al once there's
actually an act of intercourse. So why here is she forbidden to
him? So earlier the גמרא Gemara said that it was because of
גזל, gezel, right, that because it was designated for the slave, this
woman, seeing her as a type of an object, it's like stealing
her from his slave. It doesn't say otherwise here, but רמב״ם Rambam
here actually puts it under עריות arayos of בני נח Bnei Noach
and a type of אשת איש. eshes ish. And what he says
is, is that for free, you know, a free man gentile, free
woman, marriage is defined by intercourse in the context of marriage, not
any intercourse, but in the context of marriage, בעולת בעל, be'ulat ba'al,
whereas for slaves, since I guess the reality is that slaves don't
have the same institution of marriage, we know that in general in
הלכה, halacha, presumably that was true in society, you know, very often
of course they would break up families and all those types of
things in slaves, so they don't have the same institution. Interestingly, we'll
recognize a de facto societal marriage through this idea of ייחד לו.
yichad lo. So for the רמב״ם, Rambam, the חידוש chiddush is, in
a way it's funny because it's even at an earlier stage than
intercourse, that for slaves that don't have the normal societal marriage, ייחד
לו yichad lo defines marriage. So רמב״ם Rambam puts this under עריות
arayos and under אשת איש eshes ish for בני נח. Bnei Noach.
That's how רמב״ם Rambam categorizes it. Okay, now, מאימתי, me'eimasai, when does
that state begin? אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav Nachman: מכדי קרו לה
רביתא דפלניא. mi-d'karu lah rivisa d'planya. When they call her, oh yeah,
the—the daughter—it's funny, she's the wife, but the woman of so-and-so, the
young woman of so-and-so. When she's recognized societally as being this slave's
wife or part of this slave's household, that's when that status begins.
According—again, according to the earlier גמרא, Gemara, it's a type of a
גזל, gezel, and according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, it's a type of
a marriage. ומאימת התרתה? U'me'eimas hataratah? When does she stop being considered
designated for him, stop being his wife? אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav
Huna: משיפרעה ראשה בשוק. mi-she-par'ah rashah ba-shuk. Once she is—as a non-Jewish
woman? No, I will talk about—give me a second. But that again
reflects just a societal reality and again reflects the idea that in—in
ancient society, right, married women covered their hair, right. The גמרא—even Gemara
the גמרא Gemara wants to say that, how do you know it's
דת יהודית das yehudis to cover the hair? It's not a פסוק
pasuk that says a woman must cover her hair. It's—it's implied from
the idea that the סוטה's sotah hair is undone, which implies the
idea that the societal norm was for women to cover their hair.
So therefore, this goes by societal, you know, perception and reality. So
once her hair is uncovered outside, everybody understands she's no longer designated.
So that's for a slave. For a slave, it's very clear, whether
you see it as גזל gezel or as אשת איש, eshes ish,
it's defined by those societal realities. What is the story for non-Jews?
So it's interesting that
רמב״ם Rambam says—and I—just let me see if I have it up.
I pulled it up here.
Yes,
רמב״ם Rambam says the following. Always find my—all
these
ספרים sefarim on these phones.
I know, these are amazing. You know. Okay, here. רמב״ם Rambam says,
okay: ומאימתי תהיה אשת חברו כגרושה שלנו? U'me'eimasai tihyeh eshes chaveiro k'grusha
shelanu? משהוציאה מביתו וישלחנה לעצמה. Mi-she-hotziah mi-beiso v'yeshalachah l'atzmah.
So it sounds like a גט, get, right? והוציאה מביתו, V'hotziah mi-beito,
right? והלכה והייתה. v'halcha v'hayesa. But without the גט, get, without the
גט, get, just like your divorce, okay? And like Islam, I—I think
somebody just—a man says three times, like, you're divorced, you're divorced, you're
divorced or something like that. But—but anyway, he doesn't have that. No
גט. get. או משיצאה היא מתחת רשותו ותלך לה. O mi-she-teitzei hi
mi-tachas reshuso v'telech lah.
She can divorce herself. It—divorce can be either the man initiates or
the woman. שאין להם גירושין בכתב. She-ein lahem gerushin b'chsav. ואין הדבר
תלוי בו לבדו, V'ein ha-davar taluy bo l'vado, אלא כל זמן שירצה
הוא או היא לפרוש זה מזה פורשין. ella kol zman she-yirtzeh hu
o hi lifrosh zeh mi-zeh porshin.
Okay, so the רמב״ם Rambam says either side can decide to walk
out. So it's very interesting, you know, and this is consistent with
the idea that they only have בעולת בעל, be'ulat ba'al, they don't
have אירוסין. eirusin. According to הלכה, halacha, there's an act of קידושין,
kiddushin, an act of אירוסין, eirusin, which is initiated by the man
and it's a type—thing—like as a type of a taking possession of,
but we have a whole שיעור shiur about what degree is קידושין
kiddushin like קניין kinyan or not. But anyway, assumedly initiated by the
man. The flip is the גירושין. gerushin. The same way the man,
you know, did the act of אירוסין, eirusin, he does the act
of גירושין gerushin of pushing away. It's all sort of focused on
man. The רמב״ם Rambam has it like בני נח, Bnei Noach, it's
בעולת בעל. be'ulat ba'al. בעולת בעל Be'ulat ba'al requires both of them
participating in the act, רצה הוא והיא, ratzah hu v'hi, etc. And
it's a more of a—less of a formal status of an act
of קניין kinyan and more of a de facto reality. They are
living together as husband and wife. That creates קידושין. kiddushin. There's no
formal act. Okay. Okay, it's not like קידושי ביאה. Kiddushei biah. Right,
it's not like an act of intercourse. It's like the reality of
living together as husband and wife, participating by both of them. When
that reality ends, either one decides to walk away, then the marriage
ends. So it's very almost like common law marriage and it can
be initiated by either. It's very interesting that there's some people in
Israel now, you know, because of the whole עגונה Aguna issue, right?
Because they, you know, which is that they actually want to say
we should be pushing for Jews not to do קידושין Kiddushin but
to do like marriage of בני נח, Bnei Noach, okay? Just through
like the reality of בעולת בעל, Beulat Ba'al, like go straight to
משכב Mishkav and skip the קידושין Kiddushin and then either side can
walk out on them. Whether you can actually achieve that or not
and whether בני נח Bnei Noach laws applies to Jews, anyway, it's
very fascinating that that's, you know, that this is sort of the
flip side of not having קידושין, Kiddushin, yes.
But if these two, you know, the עבד Eved and the שפחה
Shifcha I guess, were living together, they wanted to, as husband and
wife, but the רב Rav does not מיחד Meyached them?
Yeah, I don't know what those realities are. They might not have
a choice, that's true. Okay,
moving on. אמר רבי חנינא: Amar Rabbi Chanina: בן נח שבא על
אשתו שלא כדרכה חייב. Ben Noach she'ba al ishto she'lo k'darka chayav.
Now here we're in a completely different category. Not עריות, Arayot, you
know, in terms of other women and so on, but the actual
acts of marital sex. This is like bizarre that certain type of
an act of marital sex would be prohibited in בני נח. Bnei
Noach. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as it says, ודבק, Ve'davak, he shall cleave unto
his wife,
ולא שלא כדרכה. ve'lo she'lo k'darka. Now why is שלא כדרכה she'lo
k'darka not an aspect of ודבק? ve'davak? So you could have said
that it means because in a sense like the bodies don't come
together, like they're glued together in the same way, just physically. רש"י
Rashi also says based on an interesting question like whatever גמרא Gemara
elsewhere indicates that, you know, anal intercourse is painful for women, I
mean obviously it depends, some people like it, you know, whatever, want
it, but anyway, but right, so but within that assumption that it's
going to be not pleasurable for the woman, he says the emotional
ודבק ve'davak isn't there. The emotional ודבק ve'davak comes out of the
fact that both sides are getting pleasure.
We said that with a man and a man?
Well, that's true also, yeah, but he says it here too. Okay,
שמתוך שאינה נהנית בדבר אינה נדבקת עמו. She'mitoch she'eina nehenit ba'davar eina
nidbeket imo. All right, but wait, let's just finish the גמרא. Gemara.
Don't let I'll take the question in a second. Let the גמרא
Gemara say the next line.
Okay,
אלא אמר רבא: Ella amar Rava: מי איכא מידי דלישראל לא מחייב
ולכותי מחייב? Mi ikka midi de'le'Yisrael lo mechayav u'le'Kuti mechayav? Is there
anything that for a Jew it's not a transgression and for a
non-Jew it is? Now this is going to be a trope in
general, that we can't imagine, assuming there are some laws like the
גמרא Gemara is going to get to, less than a פרוטה Prutah
and so on, but in general it cannot be that this whole
thing is fundamentally not problematic for a Jew and it's a חייב
מיתה Chayav mita for or it's, you know, it's one of the
שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva mitzvot Bnei Noach. Now if you look
at the side, some have the גרסא Girsa even more: מי איכא
מידי דלישראל מותר Mi ikka midi de'le'Yisrael mutar or דלישראל שרי ולכותי
אסור. de'le'Yisrael shari u'le'Kuti assur. So actually that and that's an interesting
question in the ראשונים Rishonim about are there any problems for Jews
within anal intercourse? Fundamentally the act is not a problem, but the
question is if it leads to sort of seminal, you know, emission
outside of the woman's body, it's a whole debate in the ראשונים.
Rishonim. But the simple reading of this גמרא Gemara is that it's
completely not an issue for Jews. So how therefore could it be
חייב Chayav for non-Jews? Okay, אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so
rather רבא Rava says, בן נח שבא על אשת חבירו שלא כדרכה
פטור. Ben Noach she'ba al eshet chavero she'lo k'darka patur. No, no,
no, they can have husband and wife can have intercourse שלא כדרכה,
she'lo k'darka, but if he has intercourse with another man's wife, if
he does an איסור עריות Issur arayot שלא כדרכה, she'lo k'darka, which
we know that that's considered intercourse for Jews and that is punishable
by the death penalty if it's that type of an עריות Arayot
or כרת, Karet, by a non-Jew it's not considered intercourse to be
a transgression. Okay, so that's actually quite fascinating.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
באשתו ולא באשת חבירו. Be'ishto ve'lo be'eshet chavero. It says ודבק באשתו.
ve'davak be'ishto. So the implication of באשתו be'ishto is ולא באשת חבירו,
ve'lo be'eshet chavero, okay, and therefore, so that's the prohibition of a
married woman. But it says what can you not do with a
married woman? The act of ודבק, ve'davak, okay, ולא שלא כדרכה. ve'lo
she'lo k'darka. What's prohibited is being ודבק ve'davak באשת חבירו, be'eshet chavero,
but intercourse that's שלא כדרכה she'lo k'darka באשת חבירו be'eshet chavero is
not a transgression. Now this is fascinating because going back to the
discussion I said before about abortion and less than a שוה פרוטה,
Shaveh prutah, there are places that we see that for בני נח
Bnei Noach the formal limit, the formal sort of, you know, שיעורים
Shiurim as it were in הלכה, Halacha, that there's limits to what's
considered the act, right? Only a פרוטה Prutah is גזל, Gezel, less
than a פרוטה Prutah is not. Only a baby that's born is
considered like a life, less than being born is not yet a
life. Those don't apply to בני נח, Bnei Noach, those drawing of
the lines, like anything that's broadly included in גזל, Gezel, broadly included
in רציחה Retzicha is forbidden to בני נח. Bnei Noach. But here
by the act of the עריות, Arayot, forbidden acts of intercourse, it's
more narrowly defined than by Jews. So which I find is like
very strange. I don't know the exact explanation for that. Okay, okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי חנינא, Amar
Rabbi Chanina, עובד כוכבים שהכה את ישראל חייב מיתה. Oveid kochavim she'hikkah
et Yisrael chayav mita. Okay, by the way, all these words. originally
were not כותי Kuti or עובד כוכבים Oveid Kochavim or whatever, you
know, they were גוי. goy. Okay, but anyway. Anyway, a non-Jew,
a Gentile that hits a, that hits a Jew. Hits? Did I
say killed? No, it hit, it hit. Yeah, of course killed. Yeah,
that hits a Jew חייב מיתה. chayav misa. I said...
No, legally? Or just...
No, no, maybe it means wounds, but no, just hits. Listen. שנאמר,
she'ne'emar, and otherwise we wouldn't need it, we already covered רציחה, retzicha,
and it wouldn't only be a Jew. ויפן כה וכה ויך את
המצרי. Vayifen koh vachoh vayach es haMitzri. How did Moshe kill the
Egyptian? All he was doing was beating the Jew. Didn't say that
the Jew's life was at stake or the Israelite's life was at
stake. So you see that even the beating of a Jew, obviously
you can understand this coming from Jewish people that are living under
the oppression of non-Jews, that even a beating of a Jew is
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay. ואמר רבי חנינא, V'amar Rabbi Chanina, הסוטר
לועו של ישראל, Hasoter lo'o shel Yisrael, somebody who slaps, I presumably
a non-Jew who even
slaps... maybe a Jew... anyway, who slaps the cheek of a Jew,
right, that's a לועו lo'o is a cheek, לוע loa is... yeah,
the cheek, right? כאילו סוטר לועו של שכינה, Ke'ilu soter lo'o shel
Shechinah, like slapped God's... the... you know, the cheek of the Divine
Presence. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, מוקש אדם... Mokash adam... what? It says the jaw...
better... like a לחי. lechi.
Oh, this is the לחי, lechi, this is the jaw, here. Okay.
מוקש אדם, Mokash adam, somebody who like smites a person, ילע קודש,
yela kodesh, is like the cheek or the jaw of the Holy
One. Okay, so I... maybe... I don't know, this is completely my
speculation and I know the בבלי Bavli is usually not in the
Christian context, but I cannot help thinking of if a man slap,
you know, hit you, turn the other cheek, hits you in the
cheek, turn the other cheek. So no, if hits me, right, look,
Moshe stood up to the non-Jew who was hitting him, you know,
and it's like you just hit God, you know, it's not a
forgivable thing. All right. Anyway.
So I want to understand. So according to our law then, you
know, these two guys get into like a bar room fight and
one's Jewish, one's non-Jewish, and we can just like call this guy
to court and kill him?
What can I tell you? No, seriously. Yeah, presumably... again, whether it
meant this like in theory חייב מיתה, chayav misa, whether it's in
the legalistic sense of what they would do for בני נח. Bnei
Noach. It's like we're going to get to an idea of a
בן נח ששבת חייב מיתה. Ben Noach sheshavas chayav misa. Does that
real... שבת... Shabbat... that keeps שבת. Shabbat. Are we really going to
include that in the שבע מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach
and literally say we would execute them? Or is that more like
a חייב כרת chayav kares type of a thing? At this point
when the גמרא's Gemara saying oh this is also חייב מיתה chayav
misa and this is also חייב מיתה, chayav misa, it's not clear
to me that it means it as literal as the earlier, you
know, legalistic discussions of the שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvos. All right. Okay,
so אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, המגביה ידו על חברו, Hamagbiah
yado al chaveiro, since we're talking about hitting people, anybody who lifts
a hand against his friend to smite him, even obviously Jew and
Jew, אף על פי שלא הכה, Af al pi shelo hikah, even
without smiting him, נקרא רשע, nikra rasha, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as it's written,
ויאמר לרשע למה תכה רעך. Vayomer larasha lamah sakeh re'echa. Moshe said
to the wicked one, why would you hit your friend? Which means
that he's wicked just because, not even because he already hit, but
because תכה, sakeh, why will you hit? Not why are you hitting,
למה אתה מכה את רעך, lamah atah makeh es re'echa, but why
will you, even that already made him a רשע. rasha. Okay. Now
by the way, from the פשט pshat of the פסוקים... psukim... Oh
yeah, you know ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was like the bandit or
whatever? Yeah, it's interesting. The other thing is that for משה, Moshe,
by the way, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim,
you know, just to show you how much again as a kid
my reading of פסוקים psukim was filtered through חז"ל, Chazal, you know,
I always assumed, oh, he's the רשע rasha because he's about to
hit the friend. But the פסוק pasuk says that they were fighting,
presumably they were both hitting one another. But it was that Moshe
just like saw what was going on and identified the one he
thought was at the fault, to blame, right? So the רשע rasha
does not mean because he was about to hit. It means Moshe
saw, you know, you're getting into a fight but I see that
you're the one who's, you know, that's all your fault, so you're
the רשע rasha in this context. Michael here's just defending himself, right?
But anyway, the גמרא Gemara reads it, no, he was a רשע
rasha by virtue of the fact that he was about to hit
him. Okay. So למה הכית לא נאמר אלא למה תכה. Lamah hikisa
lo ne'emar ela lamah sakeh. אף על פי שלא הכה, Af al
pi shelo hikah, נקרא רשע, nikra rasha, even without hitting him. זעירא
אמר רבי חנינא, Ze'eira amar Rabbi Chanina, נקרא חוטא, nikra chotei, it's
a sinner, which is I think less than a רשע. rasha. שנאמר,
she'ne'emar, ואם לא לקחתי בחזקה, V'im lo lakachti bechozkah, ואם לא לקחתי
בחזקה. V'im lo lakachti bechozkah. This is by the sons of עלי.
Eli. If you don't give me the, like, sacrifices, I'll just take
them by force. והכתיב ותהי חטאת הנערים גדולה מאד, V'haksiv vatehi chatas
hane'arim gedolah me'od, the sin of the youths of Eli's sons was
very great. רב הונא אמר תקצץ ידו, Rav Huna amar tikatzeitz yado,
his hand is deserving of being cut off.
What's it got to do with hitting an...
because, oh, you're right, it's not hitting, it's more like grabbing בחזקה.
bechozkah. If I have to rip the sacrifices out of your hand,
I'll probably wind up hitting you. But you're right, it's not explicit.
רב הונא אמר תקצץ ידו, Rav Huna amar tikatzeitz yado, his hand
is deserving of being cut off, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, וזרוע
רמה תשבר, Uzroa ramah tishaveir, a lifted-up arm should be cut off/broken.
Okay, now again you think that's figurative, but רב הונא קץ ידא.
Rav Huna katz yada. Rav Huna literally in one case where it
was necessary to act this way, somebody was a habitual offender, he
cut off his hand. Yeah, that's very harsh, right. So רש"י Rashi
says obviously it was like in the context of בית דין מכין
ועונשין שלא מן הדין. Beis Din makin ve'onshin shelo min hadin. This
guy was a habitual offender and whatever and it was necessary. תוספות
Tosafot actually thinks that רב הונא Rav Huna is saying no, it
is דין. din. It gets back to Michael's question earlier, when we
say חייב מיתה chayav misa in these types of contexts... or the
hand is deserving to be cut off, are we speaking
hyperbolically, right, or metaphorically, do we mean literally? So תוספות Tosfos thinks
no, רב הונא Rav Huna actually thought that's the הלכה. halacha. It
wasn't a special קנס. knas. I'd much rather have רש״י's Rashi reading.
But even with רש״י's Rashi reading, it's still like we hear nowadays
in certain countries they cut off the hand somebody steals, right, it's
like the most horrific type of thing, right. I mean where else
do you have this in הלכה? halacha?
In הלכה halacha at most you get lashes and for the very
severe things you get מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. So that's
why רש״י Rashi says that it's שלא מן הדין. shelo min hadin.
That it was a special exception.
And when we say שלא מן הדין shelo min hadin we also
mean we can come up with other forms of punishment.
Yeah you could even be ממית שלא מן הדין. memis shelo min
hadin. But right you could also come up with new forms, that
is correct.
I was going to say ממית memis
because it's within the context, right. Yeah. Yep. Yeah.
So
what does רש״י Rashi say on that context of מאדם
אחד שרגיל לקצוץ חברו וקנסו
בכך? me'adam echad sheragil liktot chavero vekanaso bekach? Not קנס knas like
a monetary fine but like a more than what was deserving an
extrajudicial punishment,
an extra heavier punishment than what was deserved. כי דאמרינן בית דין
מכין ועונשין שלא מן התורה. kedamrinan beis din makin veonshin shelo min
hatorah. Okay. So רבי אליעזר אומר אין לו תקנה אלא קבורה. Rabbi
Eliezer omer ein lo takana ela kevura.
This person will never be able to be atoned until he's buried.
שנאמר ואיש זרוע לו הארץ. shene'emar veish zerua lo ha'aretz. A man
of the arm like the hitting for him will be the land.
That's when he'll be atoned. אמר רבי אלעזר לא ניתנה קרקע Amar
Rabbi Elazar lo nitna karka now that we're talking about land אלא
לבעלי זרועות. ela leba'alei zeruoas. It's pretty funny on the one hand
somebody that whips up his arm it deserves to be buried. On
the other hand the only people that get land being involved in
real estate is a very dirty business רש״י Rashi sort of says
you need not only hustle רש״י Rashi says a little bit of
violence also okay because everybody's always trying to take from you and
there's all these fights and so on so only these people get
the land so the לו הארץ lo ha'aretz being read in a
different way. שנאמר ואיש זרוע לו הארץ. shene'emar veish zerua lo ha'aretz.
ואמר ריש לקיש Va'amar Reish Lakish that's by the way in my
thinking before of course I could be
totally making this up but it could be totally off base is
the idea of turn the other cheek it's also I couldn't help
reading this but thinking like the meek shall inherit the earth right
so as to quote Life of Brian oh that's so life nice
because they have nothing in this world so okay it's the people
of זרוע zerua they are the ones that have the land. ואמר
ריש לקיש מאי דכתיב Va'amar Reish Lakish mai dechsiv what's meant by
the verse
עובד אדמתו ישבע לחם? oved admato yisba lechem? The one who works
his land will be sated by bread. אם עושה אדמה כעבד לאדמה?
im ose adamah k'eved la'adamah? If you really want to make a
living off of the earth you have to make yourself a slave
to it. Okay then ישבע לחם. yisba lechem. ואם לאו לא ישבע
לחם. veim lav lo yisba lechem. Don't think that you can own
a farm or whatever farm work is some of the most heavy
heaviest and demanding work
and something like rise at the crack of dawn and whatever and
requires constant effort. ואמר ריש לקיש Va'amar Reish Lakish or earlier than
the crack of dawn. ואמר ריש לקיש עובד כוכבים ששבת חייב מיתה.
Va'amar Reish Lakish oved kochavim sheshavat chayav mita. Okay back to non-Jews
and this is a famous one a non-Jew who keeps שבת Shabbos
is חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Again do we mean this literally or
hyperbolically? שנאמר יום ולילה לא ישבותו. shene'emar yom valaila lo yishbotu. By
נח. Noach. So this פשט pshat is day and night and all
these parts of nature will no longer cease but this being read
as day and night you can't stop working. Gentiles are not allowed
a day off. Okay very ironic right because how Jews had to
fight so much for a day off and no we're allowed a
day off you guys have to keep on working. Okay ואמר מר
אזהרה זו היא מיתתן. ve'amar mar azhara zu hi misatan. Now before
we had that line אזהרה זו היא מיתתן azhara zu hi misatan
remember that was just explained in the ברייתא braisa it says you
can't do it it means you're חייב מיתה chayav misa but here
we're taking it in that broader sense that it doesn't need to
explicitly be included or labeled as a חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa anything
that a non-Jew is prohibited in is automatically a חייב מיתה. chayav
misa.
It sounds more like a literal for saying that.
Yeah by the quote of that phrase it does sound that it's
bringing it more into that earlier legalistic discussion that's true. אמר רבינא
אפילו שני בשבת. Amar Ravina afilu sheini beshabbos. Even if it's not
our שבת Shabbos even if it's
a Monday or enjoy any day Sunday. But רש״י Rashi says again
רש״י Rashi himself seems to say that that's because we're making a
point even if it's not done as a רש״י Rashi דווקא davka
reads it that way even if it's not שבת Shabbos even if
it's not Sunday רש״י Rashi reads it and it's not done as
a religious day of rest it's just done as a secular day
off even that is a problem.
You can't take a day off of biking?
Yeah exactly so if you take a look at רש״י Rashi well
so the fact that they take off Sunday is even not religious
now does that mean what does it mean that it's שבת Shabbos
how much does it mean completely not doing מלאכה melacha how do
you define מלאכה melacha anyway? If you look at רש״י Rashi אמר
רבינא אפילו שני בשבת Amar Ravina afilu sheini beshabbos רש״י Rashi says
לא תימא שביתה דקאמר ריש לקיש לשום חובה קאמר דנתכוון לשבות כיום
בשבת שהוא יום שביתה לישראל או אחד בשבת ששובתים בו. lo teima
shevisa deka amar Reish Lakish leshum chova kama dehis kaven lishbos kiyom
bashabbos shehu yom shevisa leyisrael o echad beshabbos sheshovsim bo. So exactly
recognizing again I don't know if the גמרא's Gemara context but that's
the way רש״י Rashi recognized it even if it's not done in
a religious
way אלא מנוחה בעלמא קא אסר ליה רישא דלא ela menucha be'alma
ka'asar lei resha d'lo not Sunday. So רש״י Rashi does emphasize the
שני. sheini. So the גמרא Gemara says, again, wait, what about rest
on שבת, Shabbos, right? I mean Jewish slaves, and they're, right? I
mean
Jewish slaves, and they have a quasi-Jewish status. But they don't give
rest on שבת?
Shabbos? It's an interesting question.
עבד כנעני Eved Kena'ani
is like, is a Jewish slave. He has quasi-Jewish obligations, right? But
if it's, right, not עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, but he's an עבד
כנעני, Eved Kena'ani, but he still is a quasi-Jew, right? If you
had an עבד eved that you did not, weren't טובל, tovel, and
was not, didn't have quasi-Jewish status, right, so you probably wouldn't have
a חיוב chiyuv to let them rest on שבת, Shabbos, under, according
to this you might be forbidden to let them rest on שבת.
Shabbos. You do for animals. I know. Yeah, it's a very good
point. It's a very good point. Like, would the fact that they
would be a, what would be the הלכה halachah of a non-Jewish
slave that hadn't even been טובל tovel and didn't have the obligations
of an עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani, would you still be חייב chayav
to be שובת shoveis them similar to the animals? Presumably yes. Now
I don't know how that would sort of supersede this point. Let
me just finish.
But they have to work at night too.
Yeah, well, that's true. I guess at, well, maybe a few hour,
maybe a little into the night, or maybe like רש״י Rashi says
elsewhere, whatever, you know, maybe the fact that they're trying to have
little slave babies for you is their, of course that's if they're
of a certain age. Anyway, ולחשוב גבי שבע מצוות? u'lichshov gabei sheva
mitzvos? Why not count it during the seven מצוות? mitzvos? כחשיב שב
ואל תעשה קום ועשה לא כחשיב. k'chashiv shev v'al ta'aseh, kum va'aseh
lo k'chashiv. So this
again, the very question reflects the idea that the גמרא's Gemara taking
this seriously. And it says so why not list it by the
שבע מצוות בני נח? sheva mitzvos bnei Noach? So they say no.
שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos bnei Noach are only things that
you're supposed to not do, right? Don't steal, don't do this, don't
do that.
But דינים dinim is positive.
The גמרא's Gemara about to get to that. But שבת, Shabbos, the
problem is that you, right, so those are things, by שבת Shabbos
to have violated שבת, Shabbos, right, to have violated this הלכה, halachah,
this הלכה halachah you violate by being passive. The other laws you
violate by being active. So we're not including שבע מצוות sheva mitzvos
that you would violate by doing nothing. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ודינים קום ועשה הוא וכחשיב? v'dinim? Kum va'aseh hu v'ka'chashiv? What do
you mean, דינים dinim is an obligation to do something. Okay, so
if you're passive you violate דינים, dinim, so and you transgress. So
here too if you're passive you violate, you should violate שבת Shabbos
and transgress the idea of taking, doing a שבת. Shabbos. So the
גמרא Gemara says: no. קום ועשה ושב ואל תעשה נינהו. kum va'aseh
v'shev v'al ta'aseh ninhu. No, דינים dinim both has an active element
and a passive element. Why? So רש״י Rashi says the, so that
the prohibition is not, it's not only to make a court, but
it's also, this is what at least what רש״י Rashi says, to
not judge perversely, right, to not do corrupt judgment, to judge justly.
So therefore that's included because in the list because there's a dimension
in which you can transgress דינים dinim by being active, by actively
perverting justice. Whereas this is not included in the list because there's
no way you can transgress it by being active. The only way
you can transgress it is by being passive. So first of all,
that's interesting that included in דינים dinim is not just a court
system, but as we said it's imposing justice, and therefore imposing justice
means also to not count, you know, to not actively pervert justice.
But anyway, but it does seem that it's taking this שבת Shabbos
thing quite quite literally. רמב״ם Rambam reads this very different than רש״י.
Rashi. רמב״ם Rambam reads this that it's specifically around turning a weekday,
like שבת... Shabbos... or let me just say one thing. For so,
so what is the problem of a non-Jew keeping שבת? Shabbos? Why
is that an issue? So one way that's often given to understand
is sort of like, well, this is our unique thing, and you're
stealing something from us. It's like a type of a גזל. geizel.
You know, this is our unique relationship, ביני ובין בני ישראל beini
u'vein bnei Yisrael etc., and then the חידוש chiddush of the גמרא
Gemara was it's conceptually like you've stolen that idea even if you're
not doing it like on שבת Shabbos itself. Okay, but that's already
a little bit of a stretch because why are you stealing our
שבת, Shabbos, you're just doing your own thing. Okay, it is interesting,
right, the Jews started with an idea of שבת, Shabbos, so the
Christians came and they did Sunday, and then the Muslims came and
then they did Friday. Everyone decided we have to pick a separate
day because this sort of distinguishes us in our identity. So it's
very interesting the way the keeping of a שבת Shabbos day is
very connected to a sense of like a whole religious identity. Okay,
so that's one approach. No, you're sort of stealing the, it's a
type of a stealing. The sense you get from this, what רש״י
Rashi says, no, even if it's a completely just a day off
and it's not about a religious aspect, the idea you get from
רש״י Rashi is as that like, no, you know, Jews have, have
won the right to take a day off, I guess. You know,
maybe we also have this higher purpose or something. Non-Jews, you know,
why did God put non-Jews on the world? You know, in order
that you should work it and make society, so you don't have
the right for a day off. Like that's some special like gift
that we have. You have to constantly be working everything and building
society. That's your תפקיד tafkid in life. That's sort of a little
bit, I'm reading that as a subtext of what might seem to
be being said. רמב״ם Rambam makes it different. רמב״ם Rambam doesn't emphasize,
says that even when the גמרא Gemara says Monday or whatever, it
means that you do it as a religious day. And the problem
for רמב״ם Rambam seems to be in general, it's sort of the
flip side of the fact that רמב״ם... Rambam... says that שבע מצוות
בני נח sheva mitzvos bnei Noach they have to do it because
God commanded it. That's what makes it a meaningful observance of שבע
מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos bnei Noach not that they just came
to it on their own, not a natural law type of thing.
And רמב"ם Rambam in general seemed very sensitive to the idea of
creating your own religious practices. And therefore,
so therefore for him, the problem is that they're doing it as
a type of a religious observance, not because you're stealing the idea
from us as much as they're just creating their own religious identity.
Of course, that's what non-Jews have done in all their religions, that's
the phenomenon of religion is that people
have rituals
as part of their religious identity. But anyway that's the way רמב"ם
Rambam says it. So I'll just read you רמב"ם Rambam and he's
going to connect to the next discussion because the next discussion is
going to be a non-Jew that learns תורה. Torah. So anyway the
רמב"ם Rambam says the following.
I'll just read the two together. We're about to get to a
non-Jew who keeps תורה Torah who learns תורה. Torah. גוי שעסק בתורה
חייב מיתה לא יעסוק אלא בשבע מצוות שלהן בלבד. Goy she'asak baTorah
chayav misa lo ya'asok ela besheva mitzvos shelahen bilvad. Okay, not because
again it's taking away, doesn't sound like you're taking it as our
תורה, Torah, it's like no,
don't go ahead and make up new religious practices.
וכן גוי ששבת אפילו ביום מימות החול אם עשה לעצמו כמו שבת
חייב מיתה ואין צריך לומר אם עשה מועד לעצמו כלל של דבר
אין מניחים אותן לחדש דת ולעשות מצוות לעצמן מדעתן אלא יהיה גר
צדק ויקבל כל המצוות או יעמוד בתורתו ולא יוסיף ולא יגרע.
Vechein goy sheshavas afilu beyom imos hachol im asa l'atzmo k'mo Shabbos
chayav misa v'ein tzarich lomar im asa moed l'atzmo klal shel davar
ein manichim osan l'chadesh das vela'asos mitzvos l'atzman mida'atan ela yihye ger
tzedek veyekabel kol hamitzvos o ya'amod betorato
velo yosif velo yigra. ואם עסק בתורה או שבת או חידש דבר
מכין אותו ועונשין אותו ומודיעין אותו שהוא חייב מיתה על זה אבל
אינו נהרג. V'im asak baTorah o shavas o chidesh davar makkin oso
v'onshim oso umodi'in oso shehu chayav misa al zeh aval eino neherag.
So the רמב"ם Rambam takes the חייב מיתה chayav misa more like
חייב כרת, chayav kares, not literal. Okay, but the רמב"ם Rambam puts
all of these into an idea of like don't go making up
your own religion. Like, there's two religions in the world. There's Judaism
and שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvos. And therefore, keep to that system and
don't go ahead and break out and make your own, don't be
מחדש דת
לעצמו. mechadesh das l'atzmo.
So even to שבת Shabbos that what so they decided alright for...
Well that's what רמב"ם Rambam said, מועד לעצמו. moed l'atzmo.
No, but if it's a matter of a new religious practice, let's
say I have a religious practice light a מנורה.
menorah. So that's what I'm saying, every single religious every single religious
practice of non-Jews is essentially a violation of this? רמב"ם Rambam might
say yes, but what's interesting about this is, the רמב"ם Rambam says
that a non-Jew is allowed to do any מצוה mitzvah any Jewish
מצוה mitzvah sort of as part of a fulfillment of the like
a non-Jew can even do ברית מילה bris milah because God commanded
ברית מילה bris milah or could do presumably, I don't know take
the לולב lulav on סוכות, Sukkos, and could keep שבת Shabbos because
God commanded the Jews so I also want to participate in that
divine command. So if I'm doing it like in the context
of the divine command to the Jews and I want to participate
in it, רמב"ם Rambam actually says that a non-Jew gets שכר, s'char,
it's a bizarre רמב"ם. Rambam. He says it in he implies it
in הלכות מילה hilchos milah and he says it explicitly in a
תשובה. teshuvah. He says if a non-Jew wants to do a ברית
מילה bris milah לשם מצוה l'shem mitzvah you let him do it.
So it's very bizarre. If they wanted to create their own idea,
God commanded us as non-Jews to do ברית מילה, bris milah, that
would probably be מחדש דת לעצמו mechadesh das l'atzmo חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. But if I want to do ברית מילה bris milah because
God commanded Jews to do ברית מילה bris milah and I want
to be part of that, then that's actually a קיום. kiyum. So
it's a very interesting whole structure that רמב"ם Rambam sets up.
I was just going to mention for some corner.
Oh, which מצוות mitzvos they're allowed to like, yeah. The keeping of
שבת. Shabbos. Yeah I had it actually connected to because they want
to be part of the
Jewish. That's actually a good point because the normal practice is that
you tell converts when they're becoming to as you're thinking שבת Shabbos
do one thing that's not keeping שבת Shabbos because before until you
convert because you shouldn't be a גוי ששבת חייב מיתה. goy sheshavas
chayav misa. Although then there is questions like really? Like a day
before their conversion where they're
really, really פרום frum and you're asking them to do חילול שבת?
chilul Shabbos? Does it really go all the way through the process?
But Jonathan makes an excellent point. According to the רמב"ם's Rambam whole
idea, if you're doing it in the context of the ציווי tzirui
of שבת Shabbos to the Jews, it's actually not included in this.
So that's an interesting point. It's not a חידוש דת. chidush das.
And Isaiah is saying on every שבת Shabbos and ראש
חודש
Rosh
Chodesh they'll all come to...
Right, that's interesting too. Participate in the Jewish שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says oh my god we have it's just
too rich we can't run through this material anyway. ואמר רבי יוחנן
V'amar Rabbi Yochanan עובד כוכבים oved kochavim so this is the one
I just read you before from the רמב"ם, Rambam, גוי goy or
whatever or נוכרי שעוסק בתורה חייב מיתה nochri she'osek baTorah chayav misa
שנאמר תורה צוה לנו משה מורשה, shene'emar Torah tziva lanu Moshe morasha,
it's an inheritance. מורשה לנו לנו מורשה ולא להם. Morasha lanu lanu
morasha velo lahem. Okay,
which is not exactly the context רמב"ם Rambam has it. וחשבי גבי
שבע מצוות, V'chashei gabei sheva mitzvos, so okay if that's really true
why not count them in שבע מצוות? sheva mitzvos? So מאן דאמר
מורשה. man d'amar morasha. Gives you the the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* literally,
an inheritance, מיגו דגזל ליה *migo d'gazal leh*. So then it's like
stealing, you're stealing something that's uniquely ours. It's already included. And מאן
דאמר מאורסה *man d'amar me'orasah*, the דרשה *drasha* on it is that
we're like betrothed to the תורה Torah *Torah*, we're married to the
תורה Torah *Torah*, so דינא כנערה מאורסה *dina k'na'arah me'orasah*. Fine, it's
like a נערה מאורסה *na'arah me'orasah*, which is a nice כאפ *chap*
because again נערה מאורסה *na'arah me'orasah* is not naturally in שבע מצות
בני נח Bnei Noach. *sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach*, because they only have
בעולת בעל *b'ulas ba'al*. But then, for when does why does a
שבע מצות *sheva mitzvos* when would a gentile transgress נערה מאורסה *na'arah
me'orasah*? If it was a Jewish woman who was מאורסה *me'orasah*. Since
within the Jewish context, this is עריות *arayos* and it's intercourse with
a Jewish woman, therefore it's a violation of נערה מאורסה *na'arah me'orasah*.
So here the תורה *Torah*, who's the תורה *Torah* is the woman
who's married, the Jews are married. So it's like the Jewish woman
is the תורה *Torah*, and therefore you know that's like the נערה
מאורסה *na'arah me'orasah*.
So do they agree to that like דרשה *drasha*?
Again, הרמב"ם *Rambam* doesn't think that literally it means killed. מיתבי *Meisvei*,
as it says, בסקילה *baskilah*. היי רבי מאיר אומר, מנין שאפילו עובד
כוכבים ומזלות שעוסק בתורה שהוא ככהן גדול *Hai Rabbi Meir omer, minayin
she'afilu oveid kochavim v'mazalos she'osek ba-Torah shehu k'kohen gadol*? How do you
know that even a non-Jew who learns תורה *Torah* is like the
highest of high, like the כהן גדול Kohein Gadol *kohen gadol*? שנאמר,
she'ne'emar אלה המצוות אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם *Shene'emar, eileh hamitzvos
asher ya'aseh osam ha-adam va-chai ba-hem*, that a man should do and
live by them. כהנים לויים וישראלים לא נאמר *Kohanim, Levi'im v'Yisraelim lo
ne'emar*, it doesn't say כהנים, לויים, ישראלים *Kohanim, Levi'im, Yisraelim*. It's not
your classic hierarchy where כהן, לוי, ישראל Yisrael, *Kohen, Levi, Yisrael* and
then גוי *goy* would be on the outside. אלא האדם *Ela ha-adam*,
any man. הא למדת שאפילו עובד כוכבים ומזלות ועוסק בתורה הרי הוא
ככהן גדול *Ha lamadta she'afilu oveid kochavim v'mazalos v'osek ba-Torah harei hu
k'kohen gadol*. Okay, wow, that's a very powerful statement. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, התם בשבע מצוות דידהו *hatam b'sheva mitzvos did'hu*. No,
that's learning תורה *Torah* in the context of learning their שבע מצות
*sheva mitzvos*, keeping within their realm. But if they step over that
boundary and go into things that apply to us, that's a transgression.
But I should say, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as it
classically does tries to smooth over these differences. But this statement of
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, I think in a ברייתא *braisa* it's somebody
else, רב נהוראי *Rav Nehorai* or whatever, anyway, it's a list of
a whole number of statements in a תוספתא *Tosefta*, if I'm remembering
correctly, I think it's a תוספתא *Tosefta* that basically really emphasize a
very universalistic type of an ethos, and it doesn't limit it to
learning תורה *Torah*. First of all, according to one version it's עוסק
בתורה ועושה את התורה *osek ba-Torah v'oseh es ha-Torah*. It really means
doing מצות *mitzvos*. And then it quotes other פסוקים *pesukim*, it says
like,
you know, שאו שערים ראשיכם *se'u shearim rasheichem*, whatever, ויבא *v'yavo*, what
is it?
שאו שערים ראשיכם ויבא מלך הכבוד *Se'u
shearim rasheichem v'yavo melech ha-kavod*? No, but there's something about ויבא גוי
צדיק שמר אמנים *v'yavo goy tzaddik shomer emunim*. There's another פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* about ויבא גוי צדיק שמר אמנים *v'yavo goy tzaddik shomer emunim*,
and it says כהנים לויים וישראלים לא נאמר *Kohanim, Levi'im v'Yisraelim lo
ne'emar*, אלא ויבא גוי צדיק *ela v'yavo goy tzaddik*. אפילו גוי *Afillu
goy*, you know, that you know who's a צדיק *tzaddik* or עוסק
בתורה *osek ba-Torah* or עוסק במצות *osek b'mitzvos* or whatever, you know,
you know, should can enter into the gates of God, שמר אמנים
*shomer emunim*. So actually, if you look, I encourage you to look
at the cross-reference here because it's actually a nice collection of statements
that articulate a very, you know, on the one hand look, I
maybe it's a point to say this about the שבע מצות *sheva
mitzvos*. It is highly unusual, I don't know, people somebody who's an
expert in religion could go ahead and find out, but it's highly
unusual for a religious community to say somebody can actually be doing
the divine will, get עולם הבא *olam haba*, whatever it is, you
know, even without being part of our community. There's a track there's
a way of doing it to not be Jewish, not be Christian,
whatever, you know, and still be saved. So the very fact that
we lay out that there's שבע מצות בני נח Bnei Noach, *sheva
mitzvos b'nei Noach*, and a way to be a gentile and to
live a righteous life and ultimately serve God and so on without
being Jewish is itself a huge חידוש *chiddush*, I think, you know,
in terms of thinking broadly religiously. Number one, you know, with all
the claims that Judaism is a whatever it is, racist or ethnic
or whatever, you could always convert and we even have something to
say that, you know, that's open for everybody without having to be
Jewish. But but these statements about ויבא גוי צדיק *v'yavo goy tzaddik*
or, you know, האדם אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם *ha-adam asher
ya'aseh osam ha-adam va-chai ba-hem* are actually statements that actually equate, you
know, not just if you can live a life and it's also
okay, maybe it's a, you know, maybe it's a סוג ב' *sug
beis*, but it's also good. No, it actually says if you're a
righteous gentile, you know, it's equal, you know, גוי צדיק *goy tzaddik*,
אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם *asher ya'aseh osam ha-adam va-chai ba-hem*
and so on, you know, which is extremely sort of like powerful
statements
about universalist statements. It's not, you know, the most common theme in
חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*, it's more of a minority opinion. But anyway, but
this is part of a collection of statements that emphasize, you know,
equality, as long as you're doing what you're supposed to be doing,
you know, you know, you could be a גוי צדיק *goy tzaddik*.
Anyway, so but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here smoothes it over, right,
tries to fit it more into its structure and therefore limits this
to התם בשבע מצוות דידהו *hatam b'sheva mitzvos did'hu*. All right. Oh,
one last thing I just want to say about this is about
the whole, you know, הרי הוא ככהן גדול *harei hu k'kohen gadol*,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as I mentioned, the תוספתא *Tosefta* originally I
think says a גוי *goy* that keeps מצות *mitzvos* is ככהן גדול
*k'kohen gadol*, עוסק בתורה *osek ba-Torah* no, I think it's עוסק התורה
*osek ha-Torah*. עוסק בתורה *Osek ba-Torah* specifically means learning תורה *Torah*, and
that very much fits into a general other sort of relig- Jewish
whatever rabbinic trope, which is how תורה *Torah* is the big equalizer,
right? The classic statement that אפילו *afilu* you know, the whole list
in הוריות *Horayos*, כהן לוי ישראל Yisrael איש אשה *Kohen, Levi, Yisrael,
ish, isha*, whatever, that all that- hierarchy, it says that's when everything
else is equal. But if somebody is עוסק בתורה, אפילו ממזר ועוסק
בתורה הרי הוא ככהן גדול, afilu mamzer v'osek b'Torah harei hu k'Kohein
Gadol, the same כהן גדול Kohein Gadol. echo, right? שנאמר like יקרה
היא מפנינים, yekarah hee mipeninim, יקרה היא מכהן גדול הנכנס לפני ולפנים.
yekarah hee miKohein Gadol ha'nichnas lifnai v'lifnim. So there's this hierarchy, but
Torah is the levelizer. Torah is everybody can get to the highest
level. Okay, so here too it's very interesting that it also fits
into that. Even a non-Jew, right, becomes higher than a כהן גדול.
Torah allows equal access to all.
Okay, so now why are they only doing it in the context
that's the way the גמרא pulls it back? But the original statement
has that's the- and רבי חנינא בן גמליאל אומר אף דם מן
החי, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel omer af dam min hachai, even דם
מן החי. dam min hachai. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught.
All right, אך בשר בנפשו דמו לא תאכלו, Ach basar benafsho damo
lo tocheilu, זה אבר מן החי. zeh eiver min hachai. רבי חנינא
בן גמליאל אומר אף אף דם מן החי. Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel
omer af af dam min hachai. מאי טעמא דרבי חנינא בן גמליאל?
Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel? Why does it include blood? קרי
ביה בשר בנפשו לא תאכלו דמו בנפשו לא תאכלו, Karei bei basar
benafsho lo tocheilu damo benafsho lo tocheilu, because it didn't have to
say דם dam if it was only about בשר מן החי. basar
min hachai. So it means don't eat the flesh while the animal's
still alive and don't eat the blood while the animal's still alive.
ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, what would the Rabbis say? ההוא למישרי שרצים הוא דאתא.
Hahu lemishrei sheratzim hu de'ata. No, that's coming to tell you that
this is only a problem of אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
by an animal that the blood is considered to be distinct from
the flesh. But for whatever reason by rodents we consider the blood
to be like type of the flesh and therefore there's no problem
of אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai.
Okay, כי יוצא בדבר אתה אומר, Ki yotzei badavar atah omer, now
this is going back to רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, similarly the idea
of דם מן החי. dam min hachai. It says רק חזק לבלתי
אכל הדם כי הדם הוא הנפש. rak chazak levilti achol hadam ki
hadam hu hanefesh. By the emphasis of כי הדם הוא הנפש ki
hadam hu hanefesh in this פסוק pasuk about eating blood for him
for ישראל, Yisrael. it's similar to what we saw by בני נח.
Bnei Noach, It's coming to say that דם מן החי dam min
hachai is a separate problem. Okay,
ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, what would the Rabbis say to do with that since
they think that דם מן החי dam min hachai is not a
separate issue? הוא לדם הכזה שהנשמה יוצאת בו. Hu ledam ha'kazeh shehaneshamah
yotzeit bo. No, דם הוא הנפש dam hu hanefesh is not to
say blood when the animal is still breathing is a problem—I mean
it's a problem of blood, it's not a unique problem of דם
מן החי. dam min hachai. They read that the type of blood
that you transgress כרת kares for is only lifeblood, דם הוא הנפש.
dam hu hanefesh. דם הכזה Dam ha'kazeh means like the blood that
comes from like the arteries. Okay, so it doesn't have to be
שחיטה shechitah blood is the way רש"י Rashi says. It's any blood,
any—but it has to be lifeblood. It's only blood that comes out,
you know, not the first initial squirt which is not yet seen
as the blood that the life depends on. I mean technically all
the blood is the same, right? It's just that you need a
certain quantity of it. But anyway for חז"ל there was a certain
blood that was considered as after the initial squirting that was life—that
was the lifeblood and that's the thing that's the כרת. kares. But
not for the idea of דם מן הנפש, dam min hanefesh, you
know, דם מן החי. dam min hachai. Okay, so now the גמרא
says, okay, למה לי למכתב לבני נח ולמה לי למשני בסיני? Lama
li lemichtav le'Bnei Noach v'lama li lemishni be'Sinai? Now why if—if אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai was אסור assur or דם מן החי
dam min hachai was אסור assur for בני נח, Bnei Noach then
why did it have to be repeated here at הר סיני Har
Sinai according to—or אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, okay, since obviously
Jews are included in בני נח, Bnei Noach. why did it have
to get repeated? Okay, so it says like this,
כדרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. ked'Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Chanina. Like רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא. Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, D'amar Rabbi
Yosi be'Rabbi Chanina, כל מצוה שנאמרה לבני נח ונשנית בסיני לזה ולזה
נאמרה. kol mitzvah she'ne'emrah le'Bnei Noach v'nishneis be'Sinai lezeh u'lezeh ne'emrah. לבני
נח ולא נשנית בסיני לישראל נאמרה ולא לבני נח. Le'Bnei Noach v'lo
nishneis be'Sinai le'Yisrael ne'emrah v'lo le'Bnei Noach. Okay, so this is a
very
complicated idea—not complicated, it's a very bizarre idea. Any מצוה mitzvah that
was said to בני נח Bnei Noach and repeated applies to ישראל
Yisrael. and בני נח. Bnei Noach. Anything that was said to בני
נח Bnei Noach and not repeated, you would think to say applies
only to בני נח. Bnei Noach. But what he is saying actually
is applies only to ישראל. Yisrael. This is a very bizarre idea.
If it was said to בני נח Bnei Noach and not repeated—don't
ask me to explain it—it applies only to ישראל. Yisrael So had
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai and דם מן החי dam min
hachai not been repeated, I would have applied it only to ישראל.
Yisrael. So it had to get repeated so I would know that
it applies both to ישראל Yisrael. and to בני נח. Bnei Noach
I'm going to say this again because it is so confusing. If
it was said and repeated, if it was said to בני נח
Bnei Noach and said at הר סיני, Har Sinai, it applies to
בני נח Bnei Noach. and ישראל. Yisrael That makes sense. Okay, but
if it was said to—at—בני נח Bnei Noach. and not repeated, it
applies only to ישראל. Yisrael? Go figure that out. So this had
to be repeated so we would know that it still applies—still applies
to בני נח. Bnei Noach Okay, let let me just finish reading
this.
Okay, ולבני נח ולא נשנית בסיני, U'le'Bnei Noach v'lo nishneis be'Sinai, if
it wasn't repeated, לישראל נאמרה ולא לבני נח. le'Yisrael ne'emrah v'lo le'Bnei
Noach. So that's why this had to be repeated so it would
apply also to בני נח. Bnei Noach, ואנו אין לנו, V'anu ein
lanu, now what is it that was said to ישראל Yisrael. and
not repeated at הר סיני—said Har Sinai to בני נח Bnei Noach
and not repeated at הר סיני Har Sinai that applies only to
ישראל? Yisrael. So the only example of this is
גיד הנשה Gid hanasheh אליבא דרבי יהודה. aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. גיד הנשה
Gid hanasheh according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. What does it mean
according to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Because when the פסוק pasuk says
על כן לא יאכלו בני ישראל את גיד הנשה, al kein lo
yochlu Bnei Yisrael es gid hanasheh, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
that פסוק was said at that time of יעקב אבינו. Yaakov Avinu.
But the רבנן Rabbanan say no no no, this פסוק was said
only at הר סיני Har Sinai and then it was written in
the תורה earlier in the story. But it wasn't given, the מצוה
mitzvah of גיד הנשה Gid Hanashe was not given at the time
of יעקב אבינו. Yaakov Avinu. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that מצוה
mitzvah was given at the time of יעקב אבינו. Yaakov Avinu. So
that is the one thing that is said early, that is not
repeated, and that's the one thing that applies only to ישראל. Yisrael.
Of course the irony is that there it says explicitly על כן
לא יאכלו בני ישראל את גיד הנשה. al kein lo yochlu Bnei
Yisrael et gid hanashe. Okay. So one minute, but that's the basic
only thing that so it's a rule which is a completely bizarre
rule, but thankfully it really only applies to one thing. Okay. Now,
let's I just want to get to
the two dots. אמר מר, Amar mar, כל מצוה שנאמרה לבני נח
ונשנית בסיני לזה ולזה נאמרה. kol mitzvah shene'emra livnei noach venishne beSinai
lezeh ulezeh ne'emra. אדרבה, Adaraba, you should say the opposite. מדינשנית בסיני
Mide'nishne beSinai was repeated at הר סיני, Har Sinai, לישראל נאמרה ולא
לבני נח. leYisrael ne'emra velo livnei noach. It was only said to
ישראל. Yisrael, גמרא says like, okay, logically you would say that, but
the evidence is against it. מדישתי עובדי כוכבים בסיני, Mide'isti ovdei kochavim
beSinai, we know the prohibition of עבודה זרה avoda zara was repeated
at הר סיני, Har Sinai, so we know it applies to ישראל.
Yisrael ואשכחן דענשו עובדי כוכבים עלוה, Ve'ashkachan de'anshu ovdei kochavim alavah, and
we know that the non-Jews for example were driven out of Israel
and the תורה speaks about the punishments of non-Jews of gentiles for
worshipping עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So we know עבודה זרה avoda zara
was said to בני נח, Bnei Noach repeated to ישראל, Yisrael. and
we know בני נח Bnei Noach are punished, and we know ישראל
Yisrael. is punished, so that shows us that if it was said
and repeated it applies to both. שמע מינה לזה ולזה נאמרה. Shema
mina lezeh ulezeh ne'emra. We see that it applies to both. Okay,
so that's that evidence. And I just again, I just want to
get to I'm sorry, I just want to read the next two
dots again at the bottom of the page, if you could just
give me two more minutes. לבני נח ולא נשנית בסיני לישראל נאמרה
ולא לבני נח. Livnei noach velo nishne beSinai leYisrael ne'emra velo livnei
noach. So this is the crazy one. It was said only to
בני נח Bnei Noach. and not repeated. It applies only to
ישראל. Yisrael אדרבה, Adaraba, thankfully the גמרא asks the question. מדלא נשנית
בסיני לבני נח נאמרה ולא לישראל. Mid'lo nishne beSinai livnei noach ne'emra
velo leYisrael. You should say it only applies to בני נח Bnei
Noach. if it wasn't repeated. No, that we can't say. ליכא מידי
דלישראל שרי ולעובדי כוכבים אסור. Leka midi de'leYisrael shari vel'ovdei kochavim assur.
There can't be anything that would be, you know what, okay, I'm
rushing through this too fast. Let's stop here. Okay, we will pick
up with this tomorrow, but the basic answer of why אבר מן
החי Ever Min Hachay had to be repeated was because if it
wasn't repeated we would have said it only applies to ישראל. So
it had to be repeated to fit into this pattern that it
applies both to ישראל and to בני נח. But we're going to
pick up with this whole discussion tomorrow about this idea about what's
said and what was repeated, and like which things apply to בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael and which things apply to בני נח. So we'll
pick up with that tomorrow.